Andrew Mortenson

INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY PROFESSIONAL



Andrew@Mortenson.email (720) 996-4200

EDUCATION

ORANGE COAST COLLEGE

Orange, CA Computer Science

LICENSES & CERTIFICATIONS

MCP ID 317981 MCT 2002

MCSE 2002 MCSP 2006

MCSA 1996 CCNA 2002

RELEVANT SKILLS

Technology Pre-Sales Consulting

Analytical Thinker and Problem-Solver

Cost Analysis & Process Improvement

Project Team Management

Team Building & Mentoring

Technology Training & Courseware Creation

Enterprise Application Planning

Custom Application Development

Systems Integration & Migration

Active Directory Domain migration

Security Assessments & Performance Assessments

Data Center Assessment & Design

Systems Documentation

Data Center & Network Operations Virtualization

CAREER SUMMARY

Information technology professional spanning 30+ years of diverse experience in information systems, security, integration, digital forensics and application development with extensive knowledge in a wide variety of security, networking, operating systems, hardware, systems monitoring and benchmarking technics. Able to work independently with excellent organizational and time management skills.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

SENIOR SYSTEMS ENGINEER / PROJECT MANAGMENT

Implicit.Systems, Remote / Jan 2001 - Present

Provided information technology services with a successful track record providing executive level direction across various industries and technologies aligning with corporate initiatives and goals. Expertise developing cost-effective technology solutions aligning with business requirements that mature into strategic technology roadmaps, solutions, and programs driving internal improvements.

- Designed and built the IT infrastructure for P&C Poultry's new 25000 sq. ft. headquarters and food processing and distribution plant. Security, communications, building monitoring and remote accessibility were key requirements.
- Migration form Exchange 2003 to Smarter Mail 6.0 reducing licensing costs.
- Designed and installed a 32 camera Sony HD IP security camera monitoring solution with a 10 GB DVP recording server with web accessible monitoring for management.
- Created and developed a biometric employee time management hand recognition time clock solution to replace an antiquated manual hand punch process eliminating unethical "buddy punching" and reducing accounting administrative time.
- Developed a custom time management software application polling the time clocks utilizing .net C# and SQL Server 2012.
- Trained and registered 600+ employees on the new time management system.
- Created specialized accounting reports utilizing SQL server reporting services and crystal reports.

SYSTEMS, HARDWARE & SOFTWARE KNOWLEDGE

DESKTOP & SERVER OPERATING SYSTEMS

Windows Server, Windows Desktop, Apple, Linux, MS DOS

HARDWARE PLATFORMS

DELL, HP, IBM, Gateway, Super Micro, Network Engines, Compaq, Sun

ROUTERS, FIREWALLS & TOOLS

Cisco, WatchGuard, Juniper, Netoris, F5, Extreme Networks, 3COM, Checkpoint, Windows Firewall, 2000, SonicWall

MAIL & COMMUNICATION SERVERS

Microsoft Exchange, SmarterMail, iMail, SendMail, Asterisk, 3CX SIP VOIP

STORAGE, BACKUP & ANTI-VIRUS

SAN, NAS, StorageTec, EMC, Network Appliances, Data Direct, OpenFiler, Backup Exec, ArcServe, Net Backup, Norton Enterprise, Trend Enterprise, AVG Enterprise, Endpoint gateways

VIRTUAL SERVERS

MS HyperV, VMWare Server, VMWare (VDI) Virtual Desktop Infrastructure; Citrix XEN Server, Citrix XENDesktop, Citrix Access Gateway, Thin Client Terminals

MONITORING SOLUTIONS

Nagios, NetlQ, SolarWinds, Sniffer Pro, Hyperic, Big Brother, eEye Retina, WebTrends, Wireshark

DATABASE & WEB SERVERS

Microsoft SQL Server, Oracle, Postgress, Derby, MySQL, IIS, Apache, JBoss, Tomcat

BUSINESS SOLUTION PLATFORMS

SharePoint, WordPress, SalesForce (CRM), QuickBooks, Merlin (MRP), Siebel, Maximizer (CRM), Goldmine, SugarCRM

- Implemented QuickBooks Enterprise to replace outdated custom built dbase accounting software.
- Implemented a VMWare ESXi for virtual desktops to replace select warehouse desktops with dumb terminals reducing administrative maintenance costs.
- Lead a small team implementing a staging and production environment for Avanade in Seattle.
- Serviced Wells Fargo kiosk banking terminals for various office through-out Orange and LA counties.
- Worked with several clients in various projects ranging from server trouble shooting to designing and architecting system networks for new and existing companies.
- Prepare cost analyses and return-on-investment studies to aid decision makers on systems implementation of recommend equipment or software packages.
- Assessment of legacy systems or custom-developed applications with recommendations for more advanced business processes.
- Documentation of business systems utilizing flow charts, matrices & diagrams describing the logical operational steps.
- Training of managers and/or end users on usage of computer systems, programs, security policies and access systems.
- Use of object-oriented programming creating client server database ecommerce applications and plugins.
- Systems security monitoring and incident investigation of malicious activities identifying false positives verses malicious file uploads, compromised servers, SQL injections, or port scanning.

SHAREPOINT SYSTEMS ENGINEER

First American Trust, Santa Ana, CA / Jan 2009 - May 2009

Contracted to migrate two existing SharePoint sites into one Enterprise SharePoint portal. Implementation was completed ahead of schedule allowing for additional custom work.

- SharePoint Migration from 2000 & 2003 to SharePoint 2007 Enterprise.
- Redesign of the existing layout and migration of exchange public folders.
- Trained managers on workflow process and InfoPath forms usage.

SECURITY PROTOCOLS & CRYPTOGRAPHY

SSL, HTTPS, SHTTP, SSH, IPSec, PCT, L2TP, PPTP, RSA ACE/Server and RSA SecureID cards/tokens, DES, Triple DES, EEE2, EDE2, EEE3, EDE3

DESIGN SOFTWARE & DEVELOPMENT KNOWLEDGE

GRAPHICAL & MECHANICAL EDITORS

Adobe Photoshop, Adobe Illustrator, Visio, AutoCAD, AutoDesk Inventor, AutoDesk Revit, Adobe After Effects

CODING LANGUAGES & TOOLS

Visual Studio, C#, MVC, SQL, LINQ, JavaScript, HTML5, Java, Basic, Python, C, C++

PROTOTYPING & CIRCUIT DESIGN

Arduino, .Net Micro Framework , MACH 4 CNC, Linux CNC, Eagle CAD, Schematic Design, Board Layout, Circuit Repair

SENIOR IMPLEMENTATION ENGINEER

Integrien, Irvine, CA / Oct 2007 - Oct 2008

Assisted the sales team with professional services for fortune 500 companies such as Kaiser, Solectron, Flextronics, Digital Insight, United Online, General Electric and others assessing & analyzing and integrating Integrien's "Alive" predictive monitoring software.

- Developed training courseware for sales employees and clients on the use of the "Alive" software.
- Built a VMware staging and emulation environment of Windows, Linux and Solaris server with hundreds of configured services and business transaction for QA testing of beta software.
- Architected and implemented SharePoint 2007 for internal departmental communication.
- Provided occasional Level-3 support for the customer service department.
- Assisted the development team with design ideas from personal and customer experiences.
- Worked closely with the plug-in adaptor team developing scripts that extract specific metric data for the "Alive" analytics engine.

SYSTEMS ANALYST

County of Orange, Santa Ana, CA / Aug 2007 - Oct 2007

Indirect Contract for the Network Operations center of Orange County to enhanced city wide network monitoring.

- Upgraded several systems alerting systems such as: NetIQ AppManager, AttentionNS and Solarwinds.
- Researched and implemented several smart card and Biometric systems for computers and door access systems.
- Assisted in the implementation of a secure internet environment for OCILJ for the Orange County Sheriffs and local police departments.
- Created an offline Windows 2003 certificate authority server for the OCTILI.
- Performed third level support for internal customers of Santa Ana.